Hey, hey. What's up, my friend? So, let
me ask you, do you feel this way after
trading for a while? Perhaps you have
tried technical analysis, fundamentals,
price action, volume, but still you're
not seeing the results that you want. Or
how about this? You've blown up multiple
trading accounts and you have no idea
why it happens or how to avoid it.
Or maybe you've heard that there are
many different types of strategies out
there, but you do not know what works
and what doesn't. Because here's the
thing, if every strategy works, then
clearly there will be a lot more
profitable traders out there. Agree? And
of course, you know that's not the case.
Now, maybe you've traded a strategy for
a while and maybe made money with it at
the start, but eventually you give back
all your profits and more. Why is that?
Well, how about this? You're trying to
find the best indicator, the best
settings, the best strategy, but somehow
something better always comes along.
Why?
Now, if you
can relate to what I've just shared,
then you are not alone. And if you are
looking for answers, then the answer is
here. It lies in this trading pyramid
over here. You've probably never seen
this before, but don't worry, right?
What I want to share with you is that a
mistake many traders make is that they
start at the top of this pyramid. And
it's like building a house, but you're
starting with the roof first. It's not
going to work, right? So, this is why if
you want to be a profitable trader, we
need to start from the ground up with
the trading success formula. And then we
slowly progressively move up the
pyramid. And that's where we're going to
start in today's video. And I promise
you, if you understand what I'm about to
share with you today, then you have what
it takes or you'll know what it takes to
become a consistently profitable trader.
And if you apply what I teach you,
there's no reason why you can't find
trading success. Sounds good? Then let's
get started.
Now, let's have a look at the first part
of the trading success formula. The
first part is this, an H. You must have
an H in the markets. In other words,
your trading system must be something
that you can do repeatedly that yields a
positive outcome in the long run. You
might be wondering, but Raina, you know,
how do I know if my trading system, my
strategy has an H in the markets? Great
question. So, this is where this formula
comes into play because if you plug in
the numbers, okay, if you have done your
back testing, your forward testing, you
will have this numbers, right? And if
this number is positive, it means that
you have an H in the markets. So E
stands for expectancy or if you want to
call it H, I leave it to you. So E is
equals to your winning rate, your
winning percentage multiplied by your
average gain minus your losing rate,
your losing percentage multiply by your
average loss. And if this sounds
confusing, don't worry. I'll give you a
few examples so you can see how simple
this is. I think a 10 or 12 year old
will catch this pretty quickly. So let's
have a look at this. Imagine this. You
have a trading system that has a 70%
winning rate. Average gain is $80 per
trade on average. And your losing rate
is 30%, average loss is $100 per trade.
So you plug in the numbers. This
remember over here is your winning rate
0.7 from this 70% multiply by 80 which
is your average gain over here minus.3
which is your losing rate multiply by
your average loss which is 100 bucks and
you get $26. So what does this $26 mean?
This means that on average when you take
a trade you can expect to make about $26
per trade. So if you have done a 100
trades that's about a profit of around
$2,600 after 100 trades. So this example
clearly you have a positive age. If your
trading system has this matrix you have
an age in the markets. Now on the other
hand let's look at a negative age. So in
this case again winning rate 70%. Let's
say this time around your average gain
is $10 per trade on average. Losing rate
is 30% and your average loss is $100. If
you pluck in the numbers now, what's
going to happen is that you are going to
get minus23. This means on average you
can expect to lose around $23 per trade.
So if you take a 100 trades, you will be
down about $2,300 right there about
after 100 trades. Now that you've seen
the importance of an age, why your
trading system must have an age, that's
not all because you also need the second
part of the formula, which is risk
management. Risk management is all about
protecting your downside. No matter what
happens, even if you have 10, 20 losing
trades in in a row, guess what? If you
have risk management, your account
should not blow up. Your account should
still be able to recover from that draw
down. That's the purpose of risk
management. Because without sound risk
management, even a profitable trading
system will fail. Even if you have an
edge, you will still blow up. Let me
give you an example how this works. So
if you look at this, imagine that there
are two traders, John and Sally. Okay?
And let's say John and Sally, they both
have a $10,000 trading account. They
have a 50% winning rate and they have an
average of a 1 to3 riskreward ratio. So
you can imagine this. If you have a 50%
winning rate with an average of a 1 to3
risk-reward ratio, you're going to make
money in the long run. Going to make
quite a bit of money in the long run
because you have an age. You have a
positive expectancy.
But that may not be the case because it
also depends on how much you're risking
per trade. So in this case, let's say
John risk $5,000 per trade and Sally
risk $100 per trade. What would be the
outcome for both traders? Let me walk
you through. So for John is quite
straightforward. John, he risk $5,000
per trade. And the outcome of the next
10 trades is, you know, lose, lose,
lose, lose, lose. He won't even see the
wins. Why is that? Because first trade,
John lose negative $5,000. Second trade,
negative $5,000. Before he can even see
the third trade, he's wiped out. John is
kaboom, gone, right? His account is
gone. So wiped out. What about Sally? So
for Sally, I need to do a little bit
more work because she's a conservative
trader. So for Sally 1 2 3 4 five her
first five trades are losses. So you
know she when she lose she will lose
about $100 per trade because she risk
100 per trade. So I'll just put here
minus 100 multiply by five times. Okay.
In the past I used to draw it minus 100
five times and it gets a bit tiring. So
her total loss for the first five trade
Sally is down negative $500 from here.
Okay. But then because she has risk
management, she managed to leave to
fight another day. She managed to leave
to see better days ahead. And her
remaining next five trades are all
winners. And if you look at it right,
she has an average of a 1 to3
risk-reward ratio. This means on average
her winners is three times the size of
her losses. So on average her winners is
$300. The average size. And because she
had five winning trades, 1 2 3 4 5 over
here, you multiply by five. Her gains in
this case is $1,500.
But of course, that's not the net profit
because you also need to factor in the
losses she accumulated earlier. So her
net profit is $1,000 after
10 trades. And starting with a $10,000
account, that's a gain of about 10% for
Sally. So you can see, right, two
traders, John and Sally, trading the
same system with the same winning rate,
the same average risk-to-reward. One of
them blow up which is John and the other
one Si made a 10% gain on the account.
So by now hopefully you can see the
importance of risk management.
So we have covered a couple of things
over here. You need an age, you need
risk management, right? These two things
are critical for the trading success
formula. And of course that's not it
also because you also need discipline,
right? You must have discipline to
follow the rules of your trading system.
No matter what happens, right? Whether
it's raining, whether it's snowing,
whether you feel like it, whether it's
you must be disciplined because the the
fact is this, right? When you have
consistent actions, you're going to get
consistent results. And when your
actions are inconsistent, guess what?
You're going to get inconsistent
results. So that's that's a given.
So now I'll walk you through this few
scenarios which is pretty common, right?
In the world of trading, if you have, if
you're a trader, if you have an H and
risk management, but no discipline,
what's going to happen to you? I can
tell you what is going to happen. What's
going to happen is that you will get
inconsistent results. Yes, you have a
trading system that works. Yes, you have
sound risk management, but because of
your lack of discipline, sometimes you
feel like putting on trades, you put on
after six, seven, eight losers in a row,
when there's a valid trading setup that
comes, you hesitate to take the trade
because you know the fear of losses is
crippling you and you skip the trade.
And what happens when you skip that
trade? That trade is about to be a
monster winner that will recoup back all
your losses, but you missed it because
of your fear, because of the lack of
discipline. And that's what's what's
going to happen to you, right? If you
are someone who has an age and risk
management, but lack the discipline,
right? You are going to get inconsistent
results. Now, what if you are someone a
trader who has risk management and you
got discipline, but you have no age.
What's going to happen? In this case,
you are going to suffer what I call
death by a thousand cards. It's like
going down to a casino, right? You can
have proper risk management. You bring
$10,000. Each time you bet, you only bet
$ 20, $30, whatever. And if the
discipline, right, you follow the the
rules of your bet consistently. But
because the house has an edge over you,
you're going to lose in long run. You
may not lose within a few hours. Maybe
it take you a few days to lose all your
money or few weeks, but eventually in
the long run because you don't have an
age, you will lose to the casino. That's
what we call death by a thousand cuts.
And finally, the last one. What if you
have age? You have an age and risk and
discipline, but you don't have risk
management. What's going to happen?
Well, you're going to happen. What's
going to happen is that you're going to
be just like like John, right? You're
going to blow up eventually. You can
make, you know, uh you can make maybe
some money at the start, maybe due to
luck, but eventually due to the lack of
risk management, you're going to go
kapoom blow up your account.
So to sum up, this is the trading
success formula.
You must have an age plus risk
management plus discipline. And only
then can you be consistently profitable
in the long run. And this formula holds
true, right? Whether you're a day
trader, options trader, price action
trader, systems trader, whatever trader,
this formula holds true.
So now I've shared with you the trading
success formula. And some of you might
be thinking so Raina, you know, how do I
then how do I then go about finding an
edge in the markets? Great question. And
this is where we want to talk about or
rather I want to talk about the second
part of this pyramid which is your
strategies because there are different
type of strategies out there that you
can use to extract an age in the
markets. So a quick overview, these are
a few of the strategies that you can
consider. Personally, I trade all of
these different type of trading
strategies. These are this is not a
comprehensive list. There are probably
more that I've not you know put on this
slides like for example statistical
arbitrage calendar spreads and whatnot
but this tree is more than enough for
you to get very far ahead in your
trading career and of course if you want
to take it a step further you know go
and explore right even the stuff that I
have not managed to cover in this slide.
So there are different type of
strategies mean reversion trend
following and momentum and I want to
share a little bit more about such
strategies because they are they are
very applicable to retail traders. If
you are someone like me who who trades
from your home okay you don't have fast
connection like high frequency traders
and whatnot. These are strategies that
you can actually employ and profit for
the long run. So mean reversion trading
let's talk about this. So mean re
reversion trading the idea behind this
type of strategies is that you're
looking for stocks or assets right to
deviate away from their average price
just imagine like a rubber band you
stretch the rubber band right it's
extremely stretched and when you let go
of the rubber band what happens the
rubber band you know snaps back so same
thing for mean reversion trading we're
identifying asset prices that are
overstretched away from their mean away
from their average and then we want to
enter the trade in anticipation for this
snap back. So an example could be a
stock is in an uptrend. Okay. And then
it makes a a deep pullback oversold over
here at this point. A mean reversion
trader can look at this and say hm this
stock, you know, it's has deviated quite
a bit from its average price. There's a
high probability it's going to snap
back. So let me buy. Okay, a mean
reversion trader would buy. And then
when a stock makes a bounce up higher,
they would sell. For mean reversion
trading, they're look to they're looking
to capture small profits, not to write
the trend. Right? Trend is trend
following. So mean reversion traders
sometimes they also known as swing
traders they're just looking to capture
that one small bite of the move one
small piece of the move and generally
for mean reversion traders they have a
high winning rate right 60 plus some
even 70% winning rate however their
average loss is greater than their
average profit so for example if their
average loss is $100 on average their
average profit is possibly you know 70
80 or 80 plus dollars and later on in
this training I will share with you a
mean reversion trading system that works
I'll give you the exact trading rules,
when to buy, when to sell, the
historical back test data results as
well. So, it's something that you can
actually employ in your own trading if
you wish to. So, that will come later
part of the trading. But for now, let's
talk about trend following. So, you have
learned about mean reversion trading and
trend following is a different type of
approach. This is where you're trading
in the direction of the trend and riding
the trend till it ends. For a trend for
lower, your winning rate is much lower,
30 plus to 40 plus percent. And your
average profit is greater than your
average loss. Usually at least two times
your average loss. So let's say your
average loss is 100 bucks. For a trend
follower, your average profit is usually
$200 or more, right? A few times bigger
than your average loss. And a typical
trend following setup, right? Looks
something like this. Let's say stock or
whatever asset. Oh, just one thing to
add. Trend following, I would say,
originated from the futures market. You
know think of you know the turtle
traders the 1980s 1970s these are where
this group of traders or this is where
trend following was popularized where
they trade a basket of different futures
market corn wheat gold indices bonds etc
and apply a trend following approach to
them. So generally the idea is they're
looking for market to break out right
break out they buy and then they're
looking to ride the trend till it ends.
So in this case they will employ a
trailing stop loss and then only sell
when the market hits their trailing stop
loss. So thereby this for this type of
strategy they're looking to capture the
meat of the move writing trying to
capture or to write the trend till it
ends. So this is a trend following
approach. And finally the last one is
what I call momentum. Momentum approach
is very popular with stock traders where
they identify stocks that have exhibited
exhibited strong signs of momentum and
look to buy and to sell when momentum
fades. So I'll give you an example later
on but generally their winning rate can
be anywhere between 30 to 50 plus%. The
average profit is greater than their
average loss. So typical momentum
trading setup could be they look for a
stock that is in a consolidation for a
while. They look for a breakout and then
let it consolidate forming something
like a flag pattern. Then some of them
could look to buy within this flag
pattern, right? In anticipation that the
when the market breaks out of the flag,
they could capture a nice uh momentum
move up higher. So this is what momentum
trader does, right? Identifying momentum
in stocks getting in right in
anticipation that the momentum will
continue. And of course, if momentum
momentum starts to stall to reverse,
they would then get out of the trade.
And by the way, if you want to learn
more about trend following concepts, how
to write trends in the market, you can
go go down to my website
tradingwithfraer.com.
Scroll down and grab a copy of this
trading guide over here called the
essential guide to systems trading. So
in this guide, I will share with you a
trend following system that you can use
to profit in b and bare markets. I also
share with you how you can go about
developing profitable trading systems
that has a high chance of working even
if you have no experience. So all this
and more in this guide over here. It's
free. I'll put the link somewhere below
this video or you can go down to my
website directly tradingframe.com and
just grab a copy, right? Just click the
orange button and I'll send it to your
email for free.
Now we have talked about the different
type of strategies like momentum, trend
following, mean reversion.
So now the question is this right? How
do we then take this strategies and turn
it into something tradable, something
concrete, right? Because you can't just
say, "Oh, I'm a mean reversion trader."
And the next question is, "Okay, so so
when do you buy? When do you sell?" Then
you're the mean reversion trader. You
go, "Uh uh, it depends." No, no, it
can't work like that. So this is where
the third section comes into play. Okay,
trading rules. How do we use the strate
strategies the concepts of the different
strategies I shared with you earlier and
to convert it into a fixed set of
trading rules that tells you when
exactly to buy or sell or how much to
buy or sell. Okay. So this is what we're
going to talk about right now.
So trading rules are pretty much rules
based on your strategy whether whether
it's trend following mean reversion
momentum etc. Trading rules gives
purpose to your tools and indicators.
If you don't quite understand what this
means, right, don't worry. I will cover
that in dep in details later on. And
finally, trading rules allows you to
have consistent actions. And when your
actions are consistent, you're going to
get consistent results. So, what exactly
should your trading rules entail? For
me, it's very simple. Trading rules must
answer these questions. So, I'll walk
you through this, right? Number one, for
example, which markets are you trading?
Is it the stock market, the commodity,
the futures market? What are the markets
that you're trading? What time frame are
you trading? The 1 hour, the daily, the
weekly. What's the risk management? How
do you manage your risk? How do you know
how much stock to buy?
And then uh this one is important. What
are the conditions of your trading
setup? And how do you know what are the
conditions of your trading setup? This
will then ties back to the earlier
question. What's your strategy? Because
the condition for a trend following
setup will be very different from a mean
reversion trading setup. It's kind of
like you know finding a wife. What are
the conditions that you have? The girl
must have long hair, a short hair, ampit
hair. Just kidding, right? But who
knows, right? There are some guys who
who insist, right, that their wives must
have unmpited hair. I'm not here to
judge. Uh next one. When do you enter a
trade? Right? What is the entry trigger
that gets you into a trade?
And number six, when to exit if you're
wrong, right? Otherwise known as your
stop loss. It's kind of like the girl
that you're chasing, right? Going after
the girl, caught cheat, but she's not
responding. So, so when do you cut your
loss? Well, dumb guys, right? They will
average in and spend even more time and
money on those girl. Huh? And that's how
you blow up. Okay. And finally, number
seven, when do you exit? If you're
right, aka right, what's your target
profit? All right? Or if you got the
girl, when is married, when you going to
pop the question? We're going to pop the
cherry. Yeah. So, when is your where to
exit if you're right? So, all this is
what
entails right a comprehensive
trading rules if you ask me.
So, now
we have spoken about trading rules. The
question is then how do you answer the
question to these rules? And this is
where we want to talk about the tools
and indicators which is the top of the
pyramid. And if you ask me it's I won't
say it's not important but it is
secondary right relative to the earlier
components that we have spoken about
because if you don't have these three
components which I talked about earlier
your tools and indicators they are
pretty much useless. So now that you
understand the trading success formula
the type of strategies you want to
employ and the importance of your
trading rules then yes you can finally
use the right tools and indicators to
fit your rules based on your strategies.
Does it make sense?
Okay. Now, let's talk about tools and
indicators.
So, some of the different types of tools
and indicators that you might have
probably come across could be things
like trend lines, chart patterns,
support and resistance, candlestick
patterns. Indicators would be RSI, MACD,
Fibonacci, pivot points, etc. It's not a
comprehensive list. It's just to give
you an idea of the different tools and
indicators you could use or you might
have come across in your trading
journey. So question is this. What's the
purpose of your tools and indicators?
I've actually covered this earlier. The
purpose of your tools and indicators is
not to make your charts pretty to go for
Miss Universe competition. Nobody cares
how pretty your charts looks like. They
only care whether you make money with it
or not. So the purpose of your tools and
indicators is to help you develop your
trading rules which is based on your
strategy. Repeat after me. The purpose
of your trading rules, the purpose of
your tools and indicators is to help you
develop a set of trading rules which is
based on your strategy. Yeah. Okay.
And if you recall, your trading rules
must answer these questions. I bold
number four, 5, 6, 7 because this is so
important and this is where your
technical analysis, this is where your
tools and indicators come into place.
So now hopefully by now you can see how
everything is coming together, right?
You're not just blindly randomly adding
stuff to your charts because it looks
good. No, not not that way. You're
actually every tool, every indicator on
your chart, they must have a purpose.
And that purpose ties back to
the trading rules that they're trying to
serve. And that trading rules ties back
to the strategy that you're trying to
employ. And that strategy that you're
trying to employ ties back to the
trading success formula that I talked
about earlier, the ERD, having an age,
sound risk management, and a discipline
to follow your rules. All good so far,
right? Then smash the thumbs up button
and subscribe to this video if you know
it's all making sense so far.
Now, I know I've covered a lot of
material and some of it might be things
that you have not thought about before.
So let me give you an example of how you
can use the concepts that I've just
shared with you earlier and develop it
into a trading system. A trading system
that works. Okay. So let me give you an
example of it right of a trading system
that works as promised.
So overview right so the strategy that
we are going to talk about or I'm going
to teach you is a mean reversion
strategy. The trading rules it's coming
up just in the next slide. And the tools
and indicators that we using is moving
average, Ballinger band and the RSI. And
you'll see why shortly.
So to do a quick recall, a recap, right,
a mean reversion strategy for this
particular one, we are looking to
identify stocks that are in an uptrend
to make a pullback.
When the stock is oversold far from the
average price from the mean, and then
we're looking to buy and when the stock
makes a pop higher, a bounce higher,
we're looking to sell, capturing that
one swing in the market. So, how can we
then take this strategy and convert it
into a set of fixed trading rules using
tools and indicators that you're already
familiar with. So, let me show you how.
So, let's say we're going to trade the
stock market, right? This will be stocks
in the Russell 1000 index. Basically,
the largest 10,000 stocks in US time
frame is daily. Risk management is 20%
capital for each stock and a maximum of
five position. So, I'll just briefly
explain what this means. The risk
management. So let's say if you have
$100,000 trading capital, you can buy a
maximum of five positions, meaning five
different stocks. So stock A, B, C, D,
E, five stocks. And for each stock, how
much of these stocks can you buy? You
can put 20% of your capital for each
stock. So $20,000 for each stock. Okay?
So $20,000 multiply by five will be
$100,000, which is your trading capital.
So how many stocks how many of how many
stocks should you buy? If there's a
valid trading setup, then in this case
will be $20,000 which is 20% of your
capital. So this is our risk management
to it and there is no leverage involved.
Now this is the trading rules and I'm
going to explain step by step how the
indicators come into play, the purpose
of it and what not. So first one is the
stock is above the 200 day moving
average. So why are we adding 200 day
moving average to the charts? Because it
looks pretty because the institutional
traders have it on their charts? No. The
reason is simple.
It's our criteria to define an uptrend.
And when the stock price is above the
200 day moving average, we can conclude
and say, "Hey, you know, the stock price
is in an uptrend." It's kind of like,
you know, you want to make love to your
wife. You want to
hint to her. You want to ask her the
question when she's in a good mood.
Agree? You don't want to do it when her
face is black, sour
like this, right? You're probably going
to get a slap or, you know, be sleeping
in the living room or something along
those lines. So, same thing for trading.
Stock trading. We want to buy stock
that's in an uptrend in a good mood.
Yeah. So that's the reason why we have
our moving average. That's part of our
trading rules. Second one, the stock
price closes below the lower Ballinger
band. So in this case, we're using
Ballinger band to help us define the
pullback. So if you recall the mean
reversion strategy that we want to
employ is to buy on a pullback, buy on
the dip. And how do we define the
pullback? There are many ways to go
about doing it. You can use Ballinger
bands, you can use stochastic RSI and
whatnot. For this example, I'm just
using the Ballinger band to help us
define a pullback. And number three,
place a 3% buy limit order. So this is
how we actually define when a stock is
oversold. So if criteria one and two is
met and the third criteria is that on an
intraday basis, the next day the stock
price drops another 3% on an intraday
level, we will get filled on the trade
because we have this 3% buy limit order
that's being placed. So in other words,
we're kind of like catching the falling
knife, right? you know traders or
investors say don't try to catch a
falling knife but guess what we are
doing the opposite right here and I'll
show you the results shortly okay and
number four if your order is filled then
you sell when the 2-day RSI crosses
above 50 or after 10 trading days so
this is to help us define the exit
signal when to sell the when to sell our
position and we using the two-day we
using RSI over here again not because we
have to but it's just for us to define
right the bounce higher so if you recall
as a mean reversion trader, we buy on a
pullback and then when it makes a
bounce, we sell. So the 2-day RSI when
it crosses above 50 is when the stock
price will make a bounce and that's
where we sell. And of course, we don't
have to use RSI. We can say if the stock
price makes a higher close over the last
two or three days, we sell. That's fine
as well. But I'm just using the RSI
because I feel like it. Okay. And number
five, you're trading the Russell 1000.
There's thousand stocks in the index and
there are
possibly many trading opportunities.
What if you have more than five trading
setups to choose from? Which stocks do
you want to favor? So, this is where we
want to rank our stocks, the strongest
to the weaker. So, we rank them using
the rate of change or we rank them using
the increase in price over the last 150
days. So, if there are too many stocks
to choose from, we would favor stocks
that have increased the most in price
over the last 150 days. So, stocks that
have went up the most in price over the
last 150 days, those will be our top few
picks. And of course assuming that they
also follow the criterias of our trade
system over here, right? The criteria 1
to4. And last but not least, the
Ballinger band settings. I am not using
the default one. I changed it. I tweaked
it slightly. It's a 20-day moving
average in 2.5 standard deviation. I
believe the default stat settings is a
two standard deviation.
Now let me walk you through an example,
a chart example, so you can see how this
trading rules work. So of course this is
a cherrypic chart. This is a replay mode
on Trading View. And the indicators that
we are using. Yep. First one is the 200
day moving average to help us define the
trend. I'm going to change this to black
because I like it that way. Okay. 200
and click. Okay. There you have it. All
right. The stock price is above the 200
day moving average. First criteria is
met. Second one is for the stock price
to close below the lower Ballinger band.
So just look for BB baby. There we have
it. Ballinger bands. Click on this and
it pops out over here. I'm going to
change the settings to the one I shared
with you earlier. And the only
difference is the standard deviation,
which is 2.5.
Click okay. Kaboom. Okay. So, if you
look closely, you can see that right now
the stock price has closed below the
lower Ballinger band. What's our third
criteria? I think most of you can't
recall, but it's to place a 3% buy limit
order below the previous day closing
price and to see if we get filled. And
in this case this candle the closing
price is what is it 113.7. Okay 113.7.
So how do you know what is the buy limit
order to place? Very simple. Just
multiply by 0.97 since we are using a 3%
buy limit order and it gives us
let's see right the trusty calculator
says 110.29.
I just rounded up
29.
Okay. So we're going to place a buy
limit order at 110.29. 29. So in this
case, I'm just going to put this line
over here. Let's change it to 110.29.
And I click okay. So what's going to
happen is this, right? If the next day
the stock price falls and touch this
green line, we would have gotten filled
on this trade. So next day, kaching,
yep, you have gotten filled on this
trade. As you know, it touched the green
line. Now, what about exit? Our exit is
pretty straightforward. It's when the
2-day RSI
2-day RSI crosses above 50
or after 10 trading days. And if you if
you notice right 10 trading days is kind
it's actually a time based stop-loss
because there are times when you buy the
stock even though it's oversold.
There isn't any bounce. It just
continues to dip lower and lower every
single day. And of course, we don't want
to hold it till zero. It it seldom
happens. But again, we don't want to
hold it forever. We want to free up our
capital for something more for better
trading opportunities. So we're going to
hold a maximum of 10 trading days. So
this is what it means. But most of the
time we are going to exit when the 2D
RSI crosses above 50. I think more than
50% of the time you exit with when the
2D RSI crosses above 50. So if you get
the indicator out, just type in RSI
relative strength index.
Change the settings to two period RSI
just to two. I don't need the MA. Click
okay. Okay. Okay. So you can see that
right now the RSI value is 7.78. So the
moment it's above 50 that's a signal to
get out of the trade. So in this case
let's see right now it's five. Now it's
above 50. 50.47. You can see over here
that this close higher 50.47. So this is
where we need to get out of the trade.
But the market is closed. So when do we
exit? Well, we can exit on the next day
open. So what you can see over here the
next day market opened up at this price
move in our favor and we would have
exited this trade for a small profit and
that's an example of how this trading
system works and as you can see right
we're not adding
squiggly lines you know RSI moving
average for fun no every indicator on
the chart they all have a purpose for
the trading rules and the trading rules
is based on our strategy which is a mean
reversion strategy I know I'm hammering
this point over and over over and over
again because it's so important and I
feel that majority of traders just don't
understand how it all ties together.
Now, because this is an objective set of
rules, otherwise known as systems
trading, you can actually take this
rules and back test it and see how the
performance, right? How is the
performance over the last 20 plus years.
So, let's do just that.
So you can see over here over the last
25 years, this trading system has made a
profit of about 2,834%
over the last 25 years. So this equity
curve doesn't give us too much detail.
So let's dig a little bit deeper. I've
exported the data from army broker into
Excel. As you can see over here, over
the last 25 years, let's walk through
the key matrix. Annual annual return is
about 14.47%
a year. We have taken about 1,634
trades over the last 25 years. Winning
rate is 66% which is again within the
realm of uh it's pretty normal right for
a mean reversion trading system. Our
losing rate is about close to 34%. Our
average profit percentage is 4.1%
and our average loss is about 4.78%. As
you can see right, our average loss is
greater than our average profit. Maximum
draw down is 27% for this trading system
and over here yeah I just kind of like
summarized the key the key findings
earlier on Excel.
Now if you remember this remember this
formula this formula the expectancy
formula we can actually use those
numbers that we have earlier and define
what is the expectancy of this trading
system. So quick quick recap expectancy
is your winning percentage multiply by
your average gain minus your losing
percentage multiply by your average
loss. So in this case what is our
average gain and loss. So previously we
have defined it using percentages. So to
find out what is the average gain or
loss in dollar value, they just multiply
by the dollar value of the stock that
you're buying. So assuming let's say you
buy $1,000
worth of stock each time, they just
multiply accordingly. So in this case,
your average gain is 4.1% multiply by
a,000 is $41. And your average loss is
4.78. I round it up. 4.8% multiply by
$1,000, which is $48. And then you just
take those numbers and pluck it into the
formula. 66 which is your winning rate
multiply by your average gain which is
$41 minus your losing rate which is 34%
multiply by $48 which which is your
average loss and your expectancy is
$10.74.
So what this means is that on average
you make about $10.70 per trade. Now you
might be thinking what Raina I make
$10.70 per trade on average. I rather
work at McDonald's man. Yo, what's up?
I understand where you're coming from.
So bear in mind this is only one trade
and as a mean reversion trader, you will
take hundreds of trades per year and
also depending how many mean reversion
trading system you're trading. So let's
say if you take uh
I don't know 200 trades per year. If you
take 200 trades per year, that is an
average of $2,000 of profit a year. And
let's say, you know, if you can trade
bigger size, let's say instead of
risking $1,000 for each stock, you're
risking $10,000 per stock. And you stay
and you still take an average of 200
trades per year, you're looking at about
$20,000 of profit on average a year. So,
the numbers do add up. Yeah. So, as a
quick recap, here's what we have covered
today. I know it's a lot, so take your
time to digest. First and foremost, we
talk about the trading success formula.
I explained that every single profitable
trader must have this ingredient, an
age, sound risk management plus the
discipline to follow your rules for the
long haul. Then how do you go about
finding an edge in the markets? Well,
for me personally, you know, you can use
or rather I use things like, you know,
trend following, momentum, and mean
reversion. And using this strategies, I
have developed multiple trading systems.
And I highly recommend you you you know
have a look at this strategies because
it's something that retail traders can
employ on your own account. You don't
need super fast speed to the exchange.
You know you don't need to compete with
high frequency traders and whatnot. So
after knowing what strategies that you
want to employ, then you need to develop
a set of trading rules based on your
strategies and how you go about
developing your trading trading trading
rules. You can then use the relevant
tools and indicators to fit your needs.
So you don't have to, you know, randomly
or blindly add lines on the charts just
because it looks good. No, everything
now has a purpose to meet your rules.
And you know that your rules is based on
your strategies. And the reason why you
want to pick that strategies is because
it could give you an edge in the markets
that allows you to be a successful
trader in the long run. So, and by the
way, if you want to learn more about the
different type of strategies like you
know today we talk about mean reversion
but if you want to learn about let's say
trend following and whatnot you can what
you can do is also grab a copy of this
book over here called trading systems
that work. So this is a book that I've
written it's a digital copy where you
will get access to three three proven
trading systems that work because I have
rigorously tested it over the last 20
plus years. So this allows you right to
profit in bull and bare markets even
during a recession. So the first one is
a trend following system that trades the
futures markets
basically covering the forex and
commodities market and since 2000 annual
return is about 13 14%.
Then we have a mean reversion trading
system over here. This one is better
than the one I just shared with you.
This one average return of about 18% a
year since 2000. And finally we have a
breakout trading system. This one is is
a blend between momentum and trend
following and it has an average return
of about 17% a year on average. So, I'm
going to teach you these three trading
systems. I'll give you the exact trading
rules like what I did earlier, the
entries, the exits, the risk management,
so on and so forth. And here's the best
part, okay? I want this to be risk-free
for you. So, grab a copy of trading
systems that work. And if within 180
days you realize this is not for you,
just shoot me an email, okay? Just drop
me an email and I'll happily refund you
in full, no question asked. And you can
even keep the book. How's that for being
fair? Okay. So, if that's something that
you might be interested in, then just go
down to this link, trading
systemsbook.com, or I'll put the link
somewhere below this video and you can
grab a copy. And of course, if you also
want to grab a copy of the essential
guide to systems trading, this one over
here is free. Okay, this one is free,
right? You can just go down to my
website, tradingfraer.com, and grab this
one, which is free. The trading systems
book, which is this one. This one isn't
free, but it doesn't cost a lot of
money. For just 17 bucks, you can get
all the work done, all the back testing
done for you. So with that said, I wish
you good luck and good trading. I will
talk to you soon.